本期视频由CuriosityStream赞助
This episode of Primal Space is supported by CuriosityStream.
前往下方链接免费观看上千部纪录片
Watch thousands of documentaries for free by visiting curiositystream.com/primalspace.
3月2日 太空叉首次发射了载人龙飞船前往国际空间站
On the 2nd of March, SpaceX launched the Dragon 2 capsule on its first trip to the International Space Station
这次飞行的目的是在它真正载人前演示其可以安全运转
This was a test flight to show that the capsule could safely perform its job before it launches with humans onboard.
然而在真正载人之前 载人龙飞船还要进行飞行中中止测试
However before that flight takes place, the Dragon 2 capsule will need to perform an in-flight abort test,
效果会很爆炸
which could be very explosive.
本期视频 我们将了解中止系统是如何在发射失败时保护宇航员的
In this video, we're going to look at how the abort system is used
to protect the astronauts in the event of a failure.
我们还将了解现实中中止系统工作的案例
We're also going to look at real life examples of the abort system in action
以及未来太空叉的中止测试将有多酷炫
and how the upcoming SpaceX abort test might provide quite a spectacle!
在1983年 俄罗斯(苏联)打算用联盟号送两名宇航员上太空
Back in 1983, a Russian Soyuz rocket was scheduled to launch with 2 Cosmonauts onboard.
起飞前90秒 一场大火突然吞噬了整个火箭
90 Seconds before liftoff, an enormous fire engulfed the rocket.
控制小组立即触发发射逃逸系统 系统点火并把宇航员带到了安全地区
The control team triggered the launch escape system which quickly fired up and lifted the Cosmonauts to safety,
几秒后 火箭爆炸了
just seconds before the rocket exploded.
着陆后 宇航员身体并无大碍 只是吓得不轻
Upon landing, the Cosmonauts were in good health but slightly shaken,
于是赶紧给他们撮口伏特加 点了根烟冷静冷静
so they were given vodka and cigarettes to help them relax.
太空叉已经进行过发射台中止测试 可以在类似的情况中让宇航员幸免于难
SpaceX have already performed a pad abort test, which would save the astronauts in a very similar scenario.
但不是所有火箭都有发射逃逸系统
However, not all rockets have launch escape systems.
航天飞机的独特设计让它难以拥有传统的发射逃逸系统
Due to the unique design of the Space Shuttle, it wasn't practical to have a traditional launch escape system.
航天飞机的首飞 哥伦比亚号 为两名飞行员装有弹射座椅
The initial flight of Space Shuttle Columbia included two ejector seats for the pilots,
但这在航天飞机搭载超过两名航天员后就被拆掉了
however these were removed once the Shuttle started flying more than 2 astronauts.
取而代之的是宇航员可以在故障下操作的更多样的中止模式
Instead, the Space Shuttle had a wide range of abort modes
which the astronauts would carry out in the event of a failure.
其中包括飞行中打开逃生舱门 七人逃生后使用降落伞着陆
One of these included opening the escape hatch mid-flight
with all seven astronauts bailing out and using parachutes to land.
但这些中止模式都不能在像挑战者号那样突发故障让宇航员逃生
However, these abort modes would not be able to save the crew
in the event of a sudden failure similar to the Challenger disaster.
发射逃逸系统的想法最初见于NASA在60年代早期的水星计划中
The idea for a launch escape system dates back to NASA's Mercury missions during the early 60's.
当Atlas火箭发生故障时
In the event of the Atlas rocket failing,
水星号会立即点燃固体火箭 将返回舱拽离火箭
the Mercury capsule would instantly fire up solid rocket motors to pull the capsule away from the rocket.
之后阿波罗任务中的逃逸系统与之非常相似
A very similar system was used during the Apollo missions.
为了测试阿波罗的发射逃逸系统
In order to test the Apollo launch escape system,
一个指令舱的模型被安装在名为"Little Joe 2号"的助推火箭上
a mockup of the command module was placed on top of a booster named Little Joe II.
原计划是发射火箭 在一万英尺触发逃逸
The plan was to launch the rocket and trigger an abort once it reached 10,000 feet.
但因为陀螺仪设置错误 火箭开始滚转
However, due to a mistake when setting up the gyros, the booster started to roll
并马上陷入失控状态并解体
and quickly became uncontrollable, causing it to break apart.
这立即触发了中止 发射逃逸系统很快将指令舱拽离至安全地带
This instantly triggered an abort and the launch escape system quickly pulled the command module to safety.
这次无心插柳的失败却成就了一次最真实的发射逃逸系统测试
This unexpected failure provided the most realistic test for the launch escape system.
这是一次“相当成功的失败”
It was a perfectly successful failure.
载人龙飞船之后的中止测试也会是类似的流程
The upcoming abort test for the Dragon 2 capsule will follow a very similar plan.
猎鹰九号会先假装飞向国际空间站
The Falcon 9 will launch as if it was heading towards the International Space Station.
当到达最大动压时 九台梅林发动机关机 模拟推力骤减的故障
Once it reaches Max Q, the 9 Merlin engines on the Falcon 9 will shutdown to simulate a loss of thrust.
载人龙飞船会检测到该故障并与猎鹰九号火箭分离
The Dragon capsule will detect this and separate from the Falcon 9
然后立即点燃SuperDraco发动机 把飞船拽离火箭
before quickly firing up its SuperDraco thrusters to pull it away from the booster.
龙飞船之后会展开一系列的降落伞 然后溅落大西洋
The Dragon capsule will then deploy a series of parachutes before splashing down in the Atlantic Ocean.
当触发中止后 猎鹰九号会变成完全不稳定状态
Once the abort is triggered, the Falcon 9 will become completely unstable,
导致其在差不多两倍音速的时候解体
causing it to break apart whilst travelling at twice the speed of sound.
此时 猎鹰九号还载有32万磅(145吨)煤油和70万磅(317吨)液氧
At this point, the Falcon 9 will be carrying 320,000 pounds of RP-1 fuel and 700,000 pounds of liquid oxygen.
如此多的氧化剂会让燃料瞬间爆炸
This oxidizer rich environment will cause most of that fuel to combust instantly,
噼里啪啦炸成天空中一朵绚丽的烟花
creating an enormous fireball in the sky.
所以当我们耐心等待太空叉首次载人上太空之前
So as we patiently wait for SpaceX to launch their first humans into space,
不如期待一下这次中止测试 肯定非常好看
we can look forward to this abort test, which promises to be quite a spectacle.
同样好看的还有CuriosityStream的多种多样的纪录片
Another impressive spectacle is the range of documentaries on CuriosityStream.
CuriosityStream是一个拥有海量纪录片资源的视频网站
CuriosityStream is a streaming service with tonnes of interesting documentaries,
内容涵盖科学 自然 历史 科技
covering topics like: science, nature, history and technology.
我强烈推荐这部关于旅行者号探测器的纪录片
I highly recommend this documentary on the Voyager space probes,
介绍了它漫游太阳系的旅程
which looks at their wild ride through the solar system
以及它们的发现如何改变了我们对宇宙的看法
and how their discoveries changed the way we think about our universe.
CuriosityStream还有介绍霍金和大卫·艾登堡的原创内容
CuriosityStream also has original content featuring the likes of Stephen Hawking and David Attenborough.
你可以用代码优惠码"primalspace"从下方链接注册并免费观看
You can watch them all for free by visiting the link below and using the code "primalspace" to to sign up.
试用一个月内免费观看所有来自全球最棒电影制作者的纪录片
This will give you a month of free access to every documentary and non-fiction title,
from some of the world's best filmmakers.
一个月的试用后 每月只需2.99美元即可续费
After your first free month, you can continue your subscription for just $2.99 a month.
感谢观看本期视频 我们下期视频再见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.